{
  "reference_number": "2178",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "methane itself may be short lived but it is converted in the atmosphere to other greenhouse gases which live longer"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "that cost is no longer the primary concern. Balancing cost with sustainability is of course important but at least in the short term,\n\ncapital investment is required. It may be more expensive in the short term but hopefully this investment will pay back in the longer\nterm. It requires a long sighted approach from politicians, the media and the public."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "This is important but will require additional resources and may be too much for a single organisation to take on"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "In healthcare we know from studies that around 60% of our environmental impact and carbon footprint is from procurement. I am\nalmost certain that most households around the country are the same. It is easy to measure CO2e from our transport, energy etc -\n\nthese are the low lying fruits, but unfortunately only account for (at best) half of our emissions. Our clothes, chemicals, household\nappliances, the things we consume of a daily basis without thinking probably make up the other half (or 2/3) of our true\n\nenvironmental impact. As most of these things in NZ are imported from elsewhere but 'consumed' in NZ we need to make sure that\nthese are included in our calculations. I do not think currently that they are (other than perhaps their transport. This is depressing for\n2 reasons. 1 - our job already seems daunting enough, the realisation that our CO2e is perhaps twice as large as we think makes the\n\ntask so much bigger. 2 measuring this is near impossible, it will require a full lifecycle analysis of all products imported to NZ. IF we are\nserious about being truely carbon neutral rather that fudging the numbers on paper then this is what we NEED to do. We must\n\ninclude healthcare in our calculations. Anaesthetic waste gasses make up a significant proportion of healthcare CO2e but are not\nincluded in the government calculations. The anaesthetic gases from our 6 theirs last year were equivalent to the annual emissions\n\nfrom 70 family cars... Finally I feel strongly that 'sustainability' is the key. sometimes focusing only on one strand of this (carbon\nneutrality) can be detrimental to the environment in a number of other ways and NOT be sustainable. Geothermal electricity and its\nimpact of fresh water ways is a good example of this. We need to aggressively chase down our carbon targets but we also need to\n\nfocus on the wider issues of 'sustainability' for our country and our planet."
    }
  ]
}
